绝命律师
第一季 第六集
翻译  cheryl  liv  寐兮  CogitoErgoSum
翻译  依俊听杰   奶霸   肉松   红枫
校对  喃喃
时间轴  梦龙   喃喃
后期  蜡笔小新的眉毛  8T   虫虫不咬人
总监  喃喃
阿尔布开克市中心站
洗手间
麦克
Mike.
谢谢你来接我
Thanks for coming.
不谢  应该的嘛
Oh, yeah, of course.
我的车就停在街对面
I'm just parked across the street, so...
好  我...先去下...
Okay. I...I was just gonna hit the...
好  我到门口等你
Yeah, sure. I'll meet you out front.
好
Okay.
保洁的  里面没人吧
Janitor. Anybody here?
卫生棉
再高点
Higher!
还高吗  好吧  那就再高点
Higher? Okay, you asked for it.
好了  宝贝  下来吧
Oh, sweetheart. All right. Come on down.
爷爷有点累了
Pop-pop's getting tired.
别闹啦
Don't "Aw" Me.
你也稍微歇歇吧
You take a little break -- little break.
自己玩会儿吧
Go on.
真是个好孩子
A good kid.
是啊  她挺乖的
Yeah, she is.
你觉得...
So, how do you like it...
大西部怎样啊
out west?
挺好  我喜欢广阔的天地
I like it. Wide-open spaces.
好吧
Yeah.
反正和之前是不一样了
Different, anyway.
是啊
Yeah.
你最近咋样
How you doing?
我...还好吧
I'm -- yeah, I'm okay, you know?
还在适应
Adjusting.
凯莉呢
And Kaylee?
她也在慢慢适应
Yeah, she's settling in.
她还会时常问起他...
She still asks about him --
问"爸爸在哪儿"
"Where is daddy?"
她很想他
She just misses him.
好吧
Yeah.
你准备待多久  麦克
How long you in town for, Mike?
我在这儿...
I'm here...
会一直待下去
for the duration, indefinitely.
我...好多了
I'm, uh -- I'm better.
抱歉让你们等了这么久
And I'm sorry it took me so long.
我跟以前不一样了  这次是真回来了
But I'm not like I was. I'm back. I'm solid.
我想陪着你  凯莉  我的家人
I want to be here for you, for Kaylee, for my family.
那就好  你没事就好
That's good. I'm glad to hear you're better.
咋了
What?
你想说什么  亲爱的
What is it, honey?
麦克  我得问清楚...
Mike, I got to ask --
我知道我得向前看了
I mean...I know I just need to move on from this,
但有件事我一直很纠结
but I keep thinking about something.
纠结什么
About what?
就在马蒂死前
How, before Matty died,
几个礼拜
like, for a few weeks there,
他...性情大变
he was...different.
怎么变了
Different how?
我也说不清
Different -- I don't know.
变得喜怒无常
Moody, you know?
他基本上啥也不吃  也不睡觉
He barely ate. H-he wasn't sleeping.
因为鸡毛蒜皮的小事就跟我吵架
He snapped at me about the stupidest things.
我以为他是工作不顺
I started to think something's up at work
或是有人病了什么的
or -- or someone's sick, something like that,
但他不愿跟我说  把自己封闭了起来
but he wouldn't talk to me. He clammed right up.
警察嘛  不愿吐露心事  你也知道
Cops aren't real touchy-feely. You know that.
没错
No.
你说得也是
They're not. No.
但这不是什么"男儿有泪不轻弹"
But this wasn't the normal "Tough guys don't cry" crap.
这里头肯定有问题...  你没发现吗
This was more. I mean... did you notice?
你没发现他的转变吗
I mean, did you feel anything like that from him?
没...  我没看出来
I don't -- as far as I remember, he seemed okay.
我觉得他挺正常的
He seemed okay to me.
我后来想着...  我...
Well, I started to think -- I'm --
我都不知道该怎么想
I don't know. I didn't know what to think.
之后...  他死前大概三四天吧
But then...three days or -- or four --
我记不太清了
I don't remember --
凌晨两点半电话响了
But before he died, there was this phone call.
我醒了  发现马蒂没在床上
2:30 in the morning, I wake up, and Matty's not in bed.
我听见他在楼下说话
And I hear him. He's talking downstairs.
我就躲在楼梯上偷听
So...I go to listen on the stairs, where he couldn't see.
他当时很生气
He gets intense.
尽管他在低声说话
Like, he'd be screaming
但好像随时会大叫  你知道吗
if he wasn't whispering, you know?
马蒂很少生气的  他总是看得很开
Matty didn't get worked up. He'd let things go.
但这次不一样  他非常生气
But -- but this -- I mean, he was angry.
他真的非常生气
He was really angry.
他当时在说什么
What was he saying?
我听不太清楚  是关于...
I couldn't make it out. It was something about...
我不知道  我听不清
I don't know. I couldn't hear it.
但第二天早上  我问他
But the next morning, I called him out --
"昨晚怎么了  发生什么事了"
"What the hell was that about? What's going on?"
可他不肯跟我说
And he wouldn't talk to me.
但我想...
But I think...
我想他是在跟你说话
I think he was talking to you.
我吗
Me?
还会有谁呢
I mean, who else?
有那么一刻
For one hot second,
我想他是不是有外遇了
I thought maybe he was catting around --
不  他不会那样做的
No, he wouldn't do that.
是的  我知道  但是你...
No, I know. I know that. But you --
他知道如果有困难随时可以找你
He knew he could call you anytime he had a problem.
你们俩那么亲密无间
You were thick as thieves, the two of you.
他的声音有些奇怪
And there was something in his voice.
他说话的方式
It was... how he was talking.
让我觉得他就是在跟你说话
It makes me think it was you.
史黛西  我想那不是我
Stace, I don't think it was.
我不记得跟他有过深夜谈心
I can't recall any late-night heart-to-hearts with him,
那个时候没有
not around then.
可能是他的线人或者什么案子
Maybe it was a C.I. or a case.
听我说
Listen.
我知道你在做什么  一遍又一遍回想
I know what you're doing -- replaying it over and over,
想着  "如果我当时意识到了什么
thinking, "If I'd noticed this or changed that,
也许结果就不会是这样"
maybe I could have done something."
你觉得我没这样想过吗  我也有
You don't think I haven't had those thoughts? I do.
每天都在想
Every day.
你不能再这样自责下去了
You got to quit beating yourself up like this.
马蒂不在了
Matty's gone.
就是这样
That's really all there is to it.
是啊
Yeah.
我想是吧
I guess that's that.
时候不早了
It's getting on.
我该去给凯莉做晚饭
I got to...get Kaylee her dinner
哄她上床睡觉了
and put her to bed.
是啊
Uh, yeah.
好吧
Okay.
如果你需要我过来照看她  我...
Well, if you want me to drop by and keep an eye on her, I...
我愿意帮忙
I want to help.
回头见
See you around.
去哪
Where to?
出租车驾驶员许可证
你叫弗朗西斯科
"Francisco."
是我
Yeah.
你很了解这个小镇吗
You know this town?
是的  当然
Yeah, sure.
有多了解
How well?
这是你自己缝的吗
You sew this up yourself?
还不赖
Not bad.
这里肯定有个故事吧
Bet there's a story there.
-每个伤口背后都有故事  -是的
- Isn't there always? - Yeah.
好了  疼一下
All right. Little sting here.
好了  应该可以了
Okay. That ought to do it.
现在...
Now...
不要剧烈运动
...you're gonna want to take it easy.
保持清洁
Keep it clean.
保持干燥  慢慢就愈合了
Keep it dry. Let it heal.
在路易斯安大道那边有个沃尔格林[药店]
There's a Walgreens a couple blocks over on Louisiana.
可以去那里买一个悬带
Maybe go get yourself a sling.
你这里没有吗
You don't have one?
抱歉
Sorry.
-有套在脖子上的喇叭筒  -我知道
- Got a cone you can put around your neck. - Yeah.
都差不多  是吧
It's about the same, right?
五百块钱是吗
So, it's gonna be $500?
五百块
$500.
我可以给你一点止痛药
I can, uh, throw some pills in for the pain.
这药是维柯丁[止痛药]
This stuff's essentially vicodin.
二十五块一颗卖给你
I can give it to you for $25 a pill --
少给十块也行
Maybe drop the price to $15
这药毕竟不是给人吃的
for something a little less human-centric.
我吃点阿司匹林就行
I'm an aspirin man.
这样吧  送你几片
Tell you what -- take a couple on the house.
说不定你就想吃了呢
in case you change your mind.
你是这儿新来的吧
You new in town?
是的
Yeah.
是路过还是要待一阵
Passing through or sticking around?
怎么了
Why?
就是问问
No reason.
如果你想搬来迷人之地[新墨西哥州]
It's just, if you're relocating to the Land of Enchantment,
我倒是认识些人
I know people.
可以给你找份工作
I could get you some work.
那种工作我可不要
I am not looking for that kind of work,
不过  还是谢谢你
but -- ohh -- thanks.
真不明白为什么要搞成这样
Don't know why it has to be this way.
在你家好好地谈不行吗
Could have been friendly. Could have talked in your house.
你真要走正式流程吗
You really want the formal treatment?
我要律师
Lawyer.
行了  麦克
Come on, Mike.
就问你几个问题而已
It's just a couple of questions.
没什么大不了的
ain't nothing but a thing.
我要律师
Lawyer.
你又没被捕
You're not under arrest.
谁说你"被捕"了吗  没有
Okay, did anybody here say "Arrest"? No.
你想走就走
You want to walk, walk.
我原以为你会很配合的
I got to say, I, uh, expected more cooperation from you on this,
你我都是警察嘛
cop to cop.
我要律师
Lawyer.
好吧  哪位律师
Fine. What lawyer?
要立遗嘱吗  找麦吉尔
我找厄门绍特  谁知道他在哪
Ehrmantraut -- who's got him and where?
那边
That way.
伙计们  最近还好吗
Hey, fellas. How you doing?
我是詹姆斯·麦吉尔  来见我的委托人
James McGill -- Here to see my client.
怎么了
What?
马特洛克  美剧《至尊辩护律师》的主角
由安迪·格里菲斯饰演
-你看着真像马特洛克  -才不是
- You look like Matlock. - Uh, no,
应该是像扮成马特洛克的青年保罗·纽曼[演员]
I look like a young Paul Newman dressed as Matlock.
我的委托人在哪
Where's my guy?
《安迪·格里菲斯秀》里的人物
你的巴尼·法伊夫来了
Say hello to Barney Fife.
不是同一个剧  不过谢谢
Wrong show, but thanks for playing.
你怎么了
So, what happened --
是不是市长给你的贴纸不够啊
The mayor didn't give you enough stickers?
告诉我这是怎么回事吧
You want to tell me what we're doing here?
这是你的咖啡
Oh, here's your coffee.
希望是滴滴香浓意犹未尽
Hope it's good to the last drop,
因为我要为它收你一小时服务费
'cause I'm billing you the full hour for it.
这是给你的
That's for you.
你倒挺贴心
That's very thoughtful.
你真不喝吗
You serious?
你为什么要让我带咖啡来
Why did you have me bring it to you?
听我说  一会儿你要这么做
All right, here's what's gonna happen.
外面那俩警察是从费城来的
Those two cops out there are from Philadelphia.
他们是专程来找我的
They've come a long way to see me.
他们进来以后
When they come in here,
我要和他们聊几句
we're all gonna have a little chat.
等我们聊完以后
And when it's over,
那位之前一直在做笔记的年轻警察
The young one, who's been writing in his little notebook,
就会拿起笔记本  放进他的夹克衫里
He's gonna take it and put it in his jacket.
他放好笔记本以后
And when he does that,
我要你拿着这杯咖啡  泼到他身上
I want you to take that coffee and spill it on him --
制造点小意外  就这样
Little accident, that's all.
我为什么要泼人家
And w-why, pray tell, would I do that?
因为我让你这么干
Because I'm asking you to.
你是我叫来的
It's the only reason you're here.
所以说  我在这儿是因为你想让我袭警
So I'm here because you want me to assault a police officer.
我是让你从这杯微热的咖啡里弄点出来
I am asking you to take a few ounces of lukewarm coffee
泼到他身上
and spill it on him.
这还构不成"袭警"吧
I doubt that satisfies the definition of "Assault,"
我的大律师
but, hey, you're the lawyer.
好吧  我也真是傻了
Right. How silly of me.
你就是想让我给你打掩护
All you want is for me to aid and abet
因为你想偷人家的笔记本
you ripping off that guy's notepad,
你来这儿就是要干这个  对吧
'cause that's what you're doing here, right?
你疯了吗
What -- are you nuts?
你开国际玩笑呢
You can't be serious.
你可别忘了  你还欠我个人情呢
Hey, I hate to remind you of this, but you owe me one.
一家人失踪的事我帮了你
The assist I gave you with the missing-persons problem --
你懂得礼尚往来吗
one good turn and so forth?
你想要回报吗  这就是我给你的回报
You want a good turn? Here's your good turn, okay?
我会做一个
I'm gonna behave
诚实守信  遵纪守法的执业律师
like an honest-to-god, law-abiding, licensed attorney,
因为你显然需要一个
'cause, clearly, you need one
能帮你解决这里问题的律师
with whatever the hell is going on here.
走廊里那两个家伙
Now, those two jokers out in the hallway --
我会保证他们不漏掉一丝细节
I'm gonna make sure they dot their I's and cross their T's --
一切都开诚布公
everything square and above board.
这才是我要做的
That's what I'm gonna do,
我来帮你  你开心还来不及
and you're gonna be happy as hell that I'm here.
用胡安·瓦尔德兹咖啡干坏事  不行
But this little Juan Valdez bump-and-dump -- no.
胡安·瓦尔德兹  哥伦比亚咖啡公司的虚拟代言人
我才不帮你
Not gonna happen.
先生们  我们准备好跟你们谈了
Hey, gentlemen, we're prepared to indulge you.
按照警局要求  埃斯卡莱拉警探要来旁听
Detective Escalara will be sitting in with us, as per APD policy.
你没问题吧
Okay with you, right?
我没问题
Fine with me.
行
Okay.
你有律师了  麦克  能说了吗
You got your lawyer, Mike. Can we talk already?
很好  我们说过
Great. So, like we said,
我们在调查霍夫曼和芬斯基的案子
we're here looking into this Hoffman and Fensky thing.
什么都可以说  任何信息
Yeah, and whatever you can tell us -- anything at all.
慢着
Uh, hold on. Hold on.
"霍夫曼"  "芬斯基"
"Hoffman." "Fensky."
说详细点
Fill me in.
就当我对委托人的情况一概不知
Assume I know absolutely nothing about my client here, all right?
-重新开始  -天  开玩笑吗
- Start at the beginning. - Jesus. Seriously?
别被厄门绍特先生闪烁的双眼
Look, don't let Mr. Ehrmantraut's dancing eyes
和热情达观的性格骗了
and bubbly, bon vivant personality fool you.
信不信由你  其实他不爱说话
He's actually -- believe it or not -- somewhat taciturn.
要不给你们扇会儿风吧  免得你们休克了
Shall I fan you gently, so you don't go into shock?
重新开始  行吗  从最开始说起
Start at the beginning, okay? We're talking Book of Genesis.
行  麦吉尔先生  你应该知道了
Okay, Mr. McGill, as you probably gathered,
我和桑德斯警探
we -- Detective Sanders and I --
在费城警察局工作
work for the Philadelphia Police Department,
厄门绍特先生也在那工作近三十年
as did Mr. Ehrmantraut for nearly 30 years.
费城  加油  费城老鹰[橄榄球队]
Philadelphia? Go, eagles.
厄门绍特先生有个儿子叫马特
Mr. Ehrmantraut had a son, Matt.
他之前也是费城警局的
He, too, was with Philly P.D.
当时还是个刚工作两年的新人
He was a rookie officer with about two years on the job.
他是个好警察
He was a good cop.
确实
Yes, he was.
大概九个月前  他接到报警
About nine months ago, he responded
西区有间破房子里有枪击
to a shots-fired call in some west side rattrap.
马特和他的搭档特洛伊·霍夫曼警官一起去的
Matt went in with his partner, officer Troy Hoffman.
杰克·芬斯基警长是他们的后援
They had Sergeant Jack Fensky backing them up.
不幸的是  事情失去控制
Unfortunately, things got out of hand.
他们三人中了埋伏
The three of them were ambushed,
马特没能活着回来
and, uh, Matt didn't make it out.
霍夫曼和芬斯基回击了
Hoffman and Fensky returned fire,
但开枪的人跑了
but the shooter got away.
我们跟进了一些线索  找了些嫌疑人
We chased a few leads, shook up the usual suspects --
但毫无进展
came up short.
很抱歉听到这些
I'm very sorry to hear it.
总之  我们兜兜转转
Anyways, we kept beating the bushes,
查无所获  直到三个月前
kept coming up dry until three months ago.
霍夫曼和芬斯基被发现
That's when Hoffman and Fensky both turned up dead
死在城北一片空地上
in a vacant lot out in nicetown --
好像又是中了埋伏
again, an ambush of some kind, it looks like.
这个杀了马特却逍遥法外的人
And with whoever killed Matt out there in the wind,
我们觉得  合理地推测
we're thinking -- well, it's our operating theory
霍夫曼和芬斯基肯定卷入了什么事
that Hoffman and Fensky were mixed up in something,
结果出了岔子  导致马特被杀
some bad business, and maybe that got Matt killed.
抱歉  我得尽我律师的职责问一下
Yeah, sorry. I got to do my lawyer thing here.
这和我的委托人有什么关系
Uh, what does my client have to do with any of this?
麦克  这是孤注一掷
Uh, Mike, this is a Hail Mary.
或者说大海捞针
Uh, beyond that.
要是证据确凿  线索可信
I mean, if we had any hard evidence or leads,
我们也不会找你
we wouldn't be out here.
霍夫曼和芬斯基卷入了什么事情
Now, there's anything you can tell us
你有什么想说的吗
about what Hoffman and Fensky were into?
帮帮我们  麦克
Yeah, help us out, Mike.
帮我们抓住杀了马蒂的混蛋
Help us catch the bastard who killed Matty.
霍夫曼和芬斯基我不太熟
I don't know much about Hoffman and Fensky.
他们是马特的同事  我看见过他们几次
They were Matt's people. I'd see them around sometimes.
他们被杀当晚  我看到他们在一个酒吧里
I saw them in a bar the night they died.
是麦克卢尔酒吧
It was Mcclure's --
那条红色狗很可能是麦克卢尔的
Maybe the red dog -- Probably Mcclure's.
他们当时和谁一起喝酒
Were they drinking with anyone?
是一个警察常去的酒吧
It's a cop bar.
他们和所有人一块儿喝酒
They were drinking with everyone.
你看见他们和什么特别的人在一起吗
Yeah, but did you see them with anyone in particular?
我不知道  我当时...
I couldn't tell you. I was...
你知道我当时的情况
You know how I was.
你近来过得怎么样
How you doing these days?
感觉就像是从瓶底爬出来
Feeling like I crawled out from the bottom of a bottle
努力不再落回去
and working hard to stay there.
我不得不说
Although I've got to say --
挖我的过去是没什么用的
Doesn't help much, dredging up the past like this.
那我问你
Let me ask you,
你是什么时候来阿尔布开克的
when did you come out here to Albuquerque?
不会是过了很长一段时间吧
It couldn't have been, uh, too much later.
就是在第二天到的
I think it was the very next day.
就是霍夫曼和芬斯基死亡的第二天吗
Yeah? The day after Hoffman and Fensky died, huh?
你听说这件事以后没想过留下来吗
You didn't think to, stick around once you heard the news?
我是过了堪萨斯城才听说的
I don't think I heard the news till I was west of Kansas City.
那你也
Still, you, uh --
你也没回来参加葬礼对吗
You didn't come back for the funerals, correct,
即使霍夫曼是马特的搭档
even though Hoffman was Matt's partner?
你还记得酒吧那一晚的事吗
Do you remember anything about that night at the bar?
你那时和霍夫曼或芬斯基说过话吗
Did you talk to Hoffman or Fensky at all?
抱歉  我不知道  我们不共事
Sorry. I got nothing. They weren't my people.
很遗憾你们把宝压在我身上
I'm sorry you guys took a flier on me.
希望对你们有帮助
I wish it'd have paid off.
就这样  我们可以走了吗
That it? We done here?
好了  没我们事了
We're done here, yeah.
也不是什么难事对吧
Hey, that wasn't so hard, huh?
-谢了  麦克  -不客气
- Thanks, Mike. - Yeah.
听着  我们可能会在附近待几天
Listen, we're probably gonna kick around for another couple of days,
你如果想到什么就告诉我们
in case you think of something, all right?
正好我以前从没来过西部
I've never been out west before.
见鬼
Oh! Oh, shit!
-天哪  抱歉  -搞什么啊
- Jesus. Sorry. Sorry. - Come on!
-过来  我来帮你  -有纸巾吗
- Here. I can get most of it. - You got any paper towels?
那个  我来就好了
You know what? Hey, hey. I-I got it.
-我来  谢谢  -抱歉
- I got it. Thank you. - Sorry.
看在...
For the love of...
你确定要看吗  就在我眼前
You got to do that right here, right in front of me?
里面记着什么重要内容  非得让我们
What's so important in there that we had to pull
用这种不入流的马克斯兄弟的手段
that third-rate Marx Brothers routine?
美国的戏剧团体  热衷于塑造癫狂或装傻充愣的人物
你真想知道
You really want to know?
冒着妨碍司法的风险  还是算了吧
And risk getting a piece of an obstruction rap? No, thank you.
你还有什么想问的
Anything else you want to ask?
你是怎么知道的
How did you know?
知道什么
Know what?
刚刚我会那么做
That -- that I would do that, that --
你怎么知道我刚刚会
How did you know that I would,
泼咖啡
spill that coffee?
你笑什么
What the hell's that?
你什么意思
What's supposed to mean?
行  你是高冷硬汉
Okay, great. You're the strong, silent type.
好样的
Hooray for you.
但我还是要提醒你
But in case you missed it,
你那两个费城来的朋友
your friends from Philly back there --
他们认为是你杀了两个警察
They think you killed two cops.
我知道
Yep.
警官保罗·格兰特  无消息
时间
晚十点  芬斯基/霍夫曼
马特死亡
一周后  麦克退休
三个月后  史黛西搬到阿尔布开克
是我
Yeah, it's me.
我们得谈谈
We need to talk.
你叫的警察
You call the cops?
-什么  -费城警局  是你报的警吗
- What? - Philadelphia P.D. -- did you call them?
-是  是我  -为什么
- Y-yeah, I did. - Why?
我告诉他们我听说了
Well, I told them I heard about
霍夫曼和芬斯基的事
Hoffman and Fensky--
还有什么
And what?
你不觉得这很奇怪吗
And you don't think it's strange?
先是马特
First Matt,
然后不到六个月  他的搭档和队长也出了事
then not six months later, his partner and his sergeant?
是我打电话让他们帮忙抓到杀死马蒂的凶手
Yeah, I called them to help catch Matty's killer.
麦克  如果是同一个人呢
Mike, what if the same person,
要是那个杀死马蒂的人
if the -- what if the piece of shit who got Matty
也杀死了那两个人呢
got them, too?
你到底和他们说了什么
And what exactly did you tell them?
-我告诉他们  -你告诉他们马特不干净
- I told them -- - You tell them Matt was dirty --
-你是这么告诉他们的吗  -我...
- Is that what you told them? - I --
你怎么能那么想
How could you possibly think that?
那是你丈夫  你孩子他爹
That's your husband, the father of your child.
我没那么说
I didn't say that.
我...我告诉他们我发现了钱
I s-- I told them I found money.
凯莉和我搬到这里后  我在拆箱时
After Kaylee and I moved here, when I was unpacking,
在一个老箱子的内层里发现的
it was in the lining of an old suitcase.
肯定是马特藏的  因为大概有
Matt must have tucked it away in there, 'cause this was cash --
五六千现金  不知道哪来的
$5,000, $6,000 from God knows where.
我们都是吃工资的
I mean, we were basically paycheck to paycheck.
他哪来的钱
Where the hell did he get it?
你为什么不来问我
Why didn't you ask me?
你为什么不来找我
Why didn't you come to me?
我不能找你
I couldn't.
我知道这样会让你很难办
I knew what it would do to you.
他先是被杀了
First, he's murdered,
然后又会让你觉得...
and then for you to think...
这会让你身败名裂的
I-it would have burned you to the ground.
你就什么都没了
There would be nothing left.
而且你也不跟我说话
And you wouldn't talk to me.
你每晚都喝得酩酊大醉
Every night, you were drinking yourself unconscious,
好像只有你失去了他似的
like you were the only one who lost him.
我不在乎他到底手脚干净不干净
Look, I don't care. He was dirty, he was clean
我不在乎
I don't care.
我只想让杀害马蒂的人
All I want is for whoever killed Matty
下半辈子都在监狱里度过
to rot in a cell for the rest of their life,
而且死后被人扔垃圾堆里
and then I want whatever's left of them
这就是我全部的念想
just dumped in the trash -- that's what I want.
我不管会牵扯出什么  有什么内幕
I don't care where it leads, what it uncovers.
我是说  就算他有什么见不得人的
I mean, what difference would it make
又有什么区别呢
if he was...anything?
我还是爱他
I'd still love him.
我还是想他  他已经死了
I'd still miss him. He'd still be gone.
马特是干净的
Matt wasn't dirty.
那就把话跟我说明白
Well, so be straight with me!
马上  告诉我  麦克
Right now. This is it, Mike.
他死之前那通电话到底是怎么回事
What was that phone call before he died?
不要糊弄我
Don't bullshit me.
那是我跟我儿子之间的事
That was between me and my son.
所以你承认是你打的
So you're admitting it was you.
他是干净的
He wasn't dirty!
你他妈的  你给我记清楚了
God damn you! You get that through your head!
我儿子是干干净净的
My son wasn't dirty!
食物饮料
啤酒
费城警局
让他自个儿哭去吧
Just let him cry it all out, okay?
老麦
Hey, Mikey.
-小霍夫曼  -麦克兄
- Young Hoffman. - Mikey boy.
-最近怎么样  兄弟  -你好吗
- What's going on, my brothers? - How you doing?
兄弟对吧
Brothers, huh?
我也很高兴见到你  好久不见了
Good to see you, too. It's been a minute.
我知道  我知道是你们俩
I know. I know it was you.
要打烊了  老麦
Closing time, Mikey.
要不我送你回家吧
Hey, how about I give you a lift home?
我没事
I'm fine.
不行  我不能让你开车  给你叫个车吧
No, I can't let you drive. Get you a cab?
不用了  我好着呢  好着呢
No, I'm good. I'm good.
别担心
Don't worry.
我把车都卖了  只有走路了
Anyway, I sold my car, so I'm walking.
谢谢
Thank you.
新墨西哥州  阿尔布开克
Albuquerque, New Mexico.
你去过吗
You ever been?
没去过
Nope.
我马上要去那儿
Well... that's where I'm headed.
那边有狼蛛
Tarantulas, they got.
我肯定不敢去
That's a big minus in my book.
我会小心的
Well, I will be on the lookout.
你要保重  朋友
You take care, my friend.
保重
Take care.
麦克
Hey, Mike.
老麦
Mikey.
要搭个便车吗
You want a ride?
我自己走路
I'll walk it.
在前面停车
Pull over here.
你在外面做什么呢
What are you doing out here?
来吧  我们载你一程
Come on. Let us drive you.
这外面比我前妻奶头还冷
It's colder than my ex-wife's tit out here.
来吧  来吧
Come on. Come on.
我自己走
I'm walking.
来吧  别闹了
Come on. D-don't be an ass.
来吧  我们带你回家  上车来吧
Come on. Let us take you home. Get in the car already.
外面很冷的
It's cold out here.
怎么啦  来吧  麦克  快上车
What? Come on, Mike. Come on.
上车
Come on.
好啦  慢点
Okay. Easy.
我们马上送你回家
We're gonna have you home in no time.
老天
Oh, god.
你干嘛呢
Hey. What are you doing?
还给我  那是我的
Hey. Give me that. That's mine.
等会儿给你
Later.
万一枪走火了咋办  对吧
We don't want you to shoot your foot off, now, do we?
老麦
Hey, Mikey.
什么
What?
老麦  你还醒着吗
Mikey, you with us?
怎么了
Why?
你刚才真是醉得糊涂了  伙计
You really tied one on good back there, buddy.
可不是嘛  喝那么多酒
Shit, yeah, he did -- put it away like they were
好像明天就要颁布禁酒令了一样
fixing to bring back prohibition.
在麦克卢尔酒吧的时候
Hey, hey, back at McClure's,
你发酒疯说胡话
you were talking out your ass,
"我知道是你们俩"
"I know it was you."
你什么意思
What's that supposed to mean, huh?
你知道些啥
You think you know what?
你有什么憋在心里
You got something you want to get off your chest,
要跟我们说说吗
Something you want to say to us?
你们杀了他
You killed him.
是你们杀了马蒂
You killed Matty.
你们平白无故就杀了他
And you killed him for nothing.
你们害怕他可能会去告发
You killed him because you were scared
所以就杀了他
of what you thought he might do.
你们让他进了那贩毒屋
You got him in that crack house...
你们设计好了的
And you staged it --
看起来像是某个瘾君子开的枪
Made it look like a junkie with a gun.
其实是你们
But it was you.
我知道就是你们
And I know it was you.
我会找到证据的
And I'm gonna prove it.
帮我把他弄出来
Help me get him out of the car.
干嘛
What?
来吧  出来  当心头
Come on. There you go. Watch your head.
好了  来吧  麦克
All right, come on, Mike,
一二一  一二一
One, two, one, two, buddy.
你先在这儿等一会儿
Now, you wait there one second.
我们会好好处理的  好吗  老麦
We're gonna work this whole thing out, okay, Mikey?
我们现在怎么办
What do we do now?
丧子之痛
Grief -- it's a bitch.
马特死于非命  让他难以承受
He couldn't live with it -- Matt dying the way he did.
老麦痛不欲生
It's too much for the old man.
所以决定饮枪自尽
So Mikey here decided to eat his gun.
真是太悲剧了  但是没有人会怀疑
It's tragic, but anyone could see this coming.
他本来就醉得只有半条命了
He's drinking himself to death.
我们就算帮他个忙
We're doing him a favor.
聪明  如果是我的话也会这么做
Smart. That's what I would have done if I were you.
麦克  我...
Mike, I...
你选择睁一只眼闭一只眼
You let some things slide and you look the other way.
你逮到一个毒贩
You bust a drug dealer
缴获的现金你一辈子都挣不到
that has more cash than you'll ever earn in a lifetime.
有些钱没有被归入证据上交  那又怎样
Some of it doesn't make it back into evidence -- so what?
你尝到了甜头  每个人都尝到了甜头
You took a taste. So did everyone else.
然后你就觉得自己安全了
That's how you knew you were safe.
就像刺杀凯撒  其实每个人都有份
It's like killing Caesar -- everyone's guilty.
马特没有拿脏钱
Matt wasn't dirty.
我拿了
I was.
那个辖区每个人都拿了
Everyone was in that precinct.
我们就是这样办事的
That's how it worked.
供出你的同伴  等于自寻死路
You turn in your buddy, you're screwing yourself.
你只能随波逐流
You go along to get along.
你随波逐流了
And you went along.
是的
I did.
是啊
Yeah.
是的
I did.
可你说马特没有
Okay. But you said Matt didn't.
对
No.
不是马特
Not Matt.
芬斯基早就找上霍夫曼
Fensky got to Hoffman early --
他们向帮派收取回扣
kickbacks from some gang or another --
也就是保护费
protection, basically.
霍夫曼来找马蒂想拉他下水
And Hoffman went to Matty and offered to cut him in.
挺公平的  不是吗  他们是搭档
Only fair, right? They were partners.
而马特的反应和你想的一样...
And Matt did what you would think --
他很纠结
He agonized.
然后他来找我
And then he came to me,
说要去找内务部
wanted to go to the I.A.,
伸张正义  告发他们
do the right thing, shut 'em down.
我的天啊  你让他去了吗
Oh, my God. And you let him?
这就是他被杀的原因
That's why he got killed --
因为他要告发别人是吗
'Cause he was gonna turn on those guys?
不  不是
No. No.
我对他说...
I told him...
你知道警察最怕什么吗
You know what a cop fears most?
胜过被枪杀  胜过一切
More than getting shot, more than anything?
是坐牢
Prison --
跟你以前逮捕的人关在一起
Getting locked up with everybody you put away.
拿这个威胁一个警察  会让他不择手段
You threaten a cop with that, you make him dangerous,
我就是这么对他说的
and that's what I told him.
我跟他讲道理
I talked sense.
这样大家都可以相安无事
No one was getting hurt.
可如果你去找内务部
But if you go to the I.A.,
哪怕你稍微表现出这种想法...
if you even look like you're going...
他有老婆  有孩子
He had a wife, a kid,
有责任
responsibilities.
接受这笔钱  用它做些好事
Take the money. Do something good with it.
我尽力了
Well...I tried.
I tried.
可他就是听不进去
But he wouldn't listen.
我儿子太倔强了
My boy was stubborn.
太要强了
My boy was strong.
他这样会把自己逼上死路的
And he was gonna get himself killed.
所以我对他说...
So I told him...
我对他说  我也干过这种事
I told him I did it, too,
我和霍夫曼一样  用卑鄙的手段过活
That I was like Hoffman, getting by,
这就是你那晚听到的那通电话
and that's what you heard that night --
我想说服他
me talking him down,
他奋力挣扎  最后没了力气
him kicking and screaming until the fight went out of him.
他一直把我当作偶像
He put me up on a pedestal...
所以我不得不向他坦白
...and I had to show him
我和其他人一样一身污秽
that I was down in the gutter with the rest of them.
他崩溃了
Broke my boy.
我把我的孩子弄崩溃了
I broke my boy.
他去找霍夫曼  接受了钱
He went to Hoffman, he took the money,
但他犹豫了
but he hesitated.
即便看上去他照他们两个的吩咐做了
Even looking like you're doing the right thing to those two
他们还是觉得他不可靠  不信任他
meant that he wasn't solid, that he couldn't be trusted.
我让马蒂去接受那笔钱
I got Matty to take the money.
两天后他们就杀了他
And they killed him two days later.
他是我所知道的最要强的人
He was the strongest person that I ever knew.
即使是为了保命  他也不会做出这种事
He'd have never done it, not even to save himself.
是我...
I was the only one --
只有我能让他像那样堕落
I was the only one that could get him to debase himself like that.
结果是徒劳的
And it was for nothing.
我让他变成了懦夫
I made him lesser.
变得像我一样
I made him like me.
到头来那群混蛋还是杀了他
And the bastards killed him anyway.
霍夫曼和芬斯基...
Hoffman and Fensky...
如果马蒂是他们杀的
if they killed Matty...
那是谁杀了他们
Who killed them?
爸  到底怎么回事
Pop...what happened?
你知道是怎么回事
You know what happened.
问题是...
The question is...
你能接受吗
can you live with it?